在这个模块中
in this module
我们再看一下动态分配器
we're going to take another look at the dynamic allocator
特别是 tcache 以外的事情
specifically everything that happens outside of tcache
现在我们已经花了相当多的时间
now we've spent a decent amount of time
谈论 tcache 和它的工作原理
talking about tcache and how it works
tcache 由许多 bin 组成，bin中chunk大小固定
we've said that tcache consists of a number of fixed size bins
这些 bin 里能容纳的最大chunk， 大小为1032B
and these bins accommodate chunks up to a size about 1032 bytes
每个 bin 最多能装 7 个 chunk
each of these bins can hold up to 7 chunks of its specific size
这些 chunk 存储在一个单链表中
and these chunks are stored in a singly linked list
单链表中next指针被safe-linking机制保护着
the singly linked list's next pointers are protected via a mechanism referred to as safe linking
safe-linking 将其与随机数异或
and safe linking uses XOR with some random bytes
使攻击者看不出next指针
to obscure the next pointer from an attacker
在谈论 tcache chunk 元数据时
when talking about the tcache chunk metadata
我们看到了一个类似这个的结构体
we saw a struct that looked similar to this
chunk 空闲时
when the chunk was free
它由若干值组成，分别是
it consisted of a number of values of
内存中前一个chunk的大小，当前chunk的大小
previous size, the current chunk size
注意size的最后3位
note that the least significant bits of the size value
是三个标志位，A M和P
have three flag values A M and P
A表示 chunk 是否是从主 arena 外分配
A indicates whether or not the chunk was allocating from outside of the main arena
M表示 chunk 是否是用mmap申请的
M indicates whether or not the chunk was mmapped
如果是1，表示是一个非常大的内存块
this would occur for very large allocations
这种情况标准堆机制没有意义
where kind of the standard heap mechanisms don't make sense
P表示前一个 chunk 此时是否在使用
P indicates whether or not the previous chunk is currently free or in use
它被成为 prev_in_use 标志
it is referred to as the previous in use flag
在利用 tcache 时
now when we are doing tcache exploitation
我们主要是利用后两个值
the primary metadata values that we messed around with were the next two
next指针，它正好在分配地址（分配地址：malloc返回值）
the next pointer which is located at the address of the allocation
和 key
and the key value
key 本身并不是很有用
now the key value itself was not very useful
但是，当没有启用 safe-linking 时
however when safelinking is not enabled
这个 key 是一个指向tcache_perthread_struct的指针
this key value is a pointer to the tcache_perthread_struct
通过它能提取一些信息
and that has some implications
然而，现在的libc中
however on a modern libc
key 是一些随机的字节
we have the key value which is just some randomized bytes
不能为攻击提供太多信息
and that doesn't provide an attack with very much information
所以我们主要用的是被加密的next指针
so what we primarily interacted with was this obscured next pointer
tcache 使用单链表来管理空闲 chunk
so we've said that the tcache uses a singly linked list to manage free chunks
它通过两个数组来完成
and it does this via two arrays
在计数数组中
in array of counts
每个整数表示对应 bin 中有多少 chunk
which is just an integer for how many entries are in a particular bin's size
在头指针数组中
and in array of head pointers
这些头指针指向空闲chunk的分配地址（malloc返回值）
and these head pointers point to the allocation address of the free chunk
空闲chunk 的分配地址处是next指针
at the allocation address of a free chunk is a next pointer
next指向先前释放的，对应bin大小的，chunk的分配地址
and that next pointer points to the allocation address of the previously freed chunk of that bin size
tcache_perthread_struct有固定个bin（不同bin，chunk大小不同）
now the tcache_perthread_struct only accommodates a certain number of bin sizes
类似的
similarly
bin链表长度有最大值
the list for a particular bin size has a maximum size
对于 tcache ，每个链表最多有7个 chunk
for tcache each of these lists can only be up to 7 chunks in length
那么当我释放第8个 chunk 会发生什么呢
so what happens when I free the 8th chunk
堆会怎么做
what is the heap going to do
我们看一下这个流程图
let's going to follow this flow chart here
所以
and so
如果能放到 tcache，我们就把它放到 tcache
if we can put it in tcache we put it in tcache
如果不能放到 tcache
if it can't go in tcache
就把它放到 fast bin 中
it's going to go into something called fast bins
下节课我们会更详细地讨论 fast bin
and we'll talk about fast bins in greater detail in the next lecture
如果放不进 fast bin
if it can't go into fast bins
那么动态分配器将检查M位是否设置
then the dynamic allocator is going to check and see if the M bit is set
M标志位是 chunk size倒数第二最低有效位
remember the M bit is a flag value in the chunk's size least significant bits
如果M标志位是1
if the M bit is set
表示它是通过mmap创建的
then the allocation was created via mmap
所以要释放它，就要调用munmap
and so to clean this up it would call munmap
如果它不能进入 tcache
now if it's something that is not able to go into tcache
也不能进入fast bin
and it's not able to go into this fast bins
那么就会放到 unsorted bin 中
then it's going to end up in this unsorted bin
unsorted bin，正如它的名字
the unsorted bin is exactly what it sounds like
它就是一个未排序列表
it is just an unsorted list
所有无法放入tcache或fast bin的，都会放到这里
where all chunks go if they don't fit into tcache or fast bins
流程图中，还有一个值得注意的是
the only other thing worth noting here in this flowchart
要是释放的 chunk 特别大呢
is that if the freed chunk is exceptionally large
在这种情况下，要是大于65KB
in this case larger than 65 kilobytes
动态分配器就会做一些清理和维护工作
then the dynamic allocator will do some like clean up and maintenance
它会清理、合并在fast bin中的 chunk
where it's going to clear and consolidate the fast bins
下节课我们会更详细地探讨fast bin
again we'll explore fast bins in greater detail in the next lecture
但值得在这张幻灯片上提一提
but it's worth mentioning on this slide
这样才会有一个完整的全局视图
so that you have a complete picture
那么malloc又是什么样呢
so what about malloc
好吧
well
malloc遵循着和此处非常相似的操作顺序
malloc follows a very similar order of operations here
只不过不是把chunk放到这些 bin 里
except instead of trying to put the chunk into one of these bins
而是从bin里取出chunk
it's going to try and retrieve them
既然是要从里面取
and since we're trying to retrieve something
我们可能不得不做一些排序
we may end up having to do some sorting or figuring stuff out
我们来看看这个流程图
so let's follow this flow chart here
首先
well first
当调用malloc
if we malloc
先尝试能否从 tcache 中取
can we get it from the tcache
如果可以，那非常好
if we can,  that's great
我们就得偿所愿了
we got it
但要是不行
but if we can't get it from the tcache
我们就去查看 fast bin
then we're going to check this thing called fast bins
如果从 fast bin里也取不出，且请求大小很小
if it can't come from fast bins and it's small
那我们就去查看 small bin
then we're going to look in the small bins category
small bin 将在下一讲中更详细地讨论
small bins will be discussed in greater detail in the next lecture
但如果申请大小不在small bin的范围
but what if it's too big for small bins
（口误）
it can't go in tcache
在 tcache 中找不到想要的chunk
we can't find what we want in tcache
在 fast bin 里也找不到
we can't find what we want in fast bins
而且想要的chunk太大了，肯定不在small bin里
and it's too big to possibly be in small bins
如果是这样的话
well if that's the case
那么就要清理 fast bin 了
then we're going to clean up fast bins
之后要查看整理 unsorted bin
and then we're going to start going through that unsorted bin pile
记住，free的时候 unsorted bin 是
right remember the unsorted bin is what happened here when we free
所有不能被缓存进 tcache 和 fast bin的chunk
everything that couldn't be cached in tcache or fast bins
的去处
went into this unsorted bin
现在
now
当malloc时
when we malloc
如果请求大小超过 small bin 的处理范围
if it's larger than the small bins can handle
就开始处理 unsorted bin
then we start going through the unsorted bin
查看里面的chunk
and we look at the chunks that are in there and
如果看到的chunk够大，可以满足malloc的要求
if the chunk that we are looking at is large enough to satisfy this malloc requirement
就返回它
then that's what will return
如果chunk不够大
if the chunk is not large enough
无法满足malloc的要求
to satisfy the malloc requirement as we're going through them
那么先整理一下
then we will sort it
也就是说，要把遇到的chunk放在small bin 或 large bin里
which means that we will place it in either the small bins or the large bins
根据它的大小
based upon its size
如果遍历完 unsorted bin
now if we've gone through all of the unsorted chunks
仍不能满足malloc的要求
and we still haven't been able to satisfy this malloc requirement
那请求的一定是一个大的chunk
then it must be something large that they're asking for
所以我们查看一下large bin
and so we'll take a look at the large bins
large bin ，正如名字所示
and the large bins as it the name indicates here
它保存大的 chunk
holds large chunks
但如果还没有任何 大 chunk 呢
but what if there haven't been any large chunks
或者 在large bin里没有找到足够大的chunk呢
and we can't find something large enough for this request in the large bins
如果它特别大
well if it's exceptionally large
那么分配器将调用mmap并设置那个M位
then the allocator will call mmap and set that M bit
但这是针对特别大的请求
but this is for exceptionally large requests
如果它只是一般大，且我们还没有free过大 chunk
if it's just large and we haven't made large chunks yet
比如，large bin还没有东西
right so like the large bins haven't been filled
我们还没开始往里放chunk
we haven't started putting stuff in there
进程可能还处在早期
because we're early in a processes you know lifetime
那我们就从 wilderness 里创建chunk
then we're going to create the chunk from the wilderness
还记得吗?wilderness是一个大 chunk
remember? the wilderness is kind of this giant chunk
它由堆中所有未转成chunk（未使用过）的内存组成
that consists of everything in the heap that hasn't been turned into a chunk
可以说是所有非chunk内存组成的一个巨大chunk
there's just like this giant chunk that is everything that isn't a chunk
我们称之为wilderness
and we refer to that as the wilderness
目光放在 tcache 之外，会发现更多的缓存机制
there's a lot more mechanisms going on once we look past tcache
除了刚刚说的这些 bin
in addition to all of these additional bins
空闲chunk中还有更多元数据
there's more metadata in the free chunks
在这里可以看到非tcache的chunk的结构
we see here that in free chunks that are not in tcache
还是有prev_size
we still have a previous size
和 size
we still have a size
size的最低3位还是A、M、P标志
we still have the A M and P flag values in the least significant bits of the size
但这里不再是 next 和 key 了
but instead of having a next pointer and a key
现在这里是前向指针（fd）和后向指针（bk）
we now have a forward pointer and a backward pointer
至于大 chunk 中
and in the case of large free chunks
还有一个 fd_nextsize 和 bk_nextsize
we also have a forward next size and a backward next size
所以在一个单独的空闲chunk中
so in a single free chunk
最多有四个指针
there could be up to four pointers
他们以不同方式导引向其它chunk
that navigate all of these chunks in different ways
为什么我们需要这么多指针
so why do we need all of these additional pointers
因为有了更多链表
well we need these pointers because there's more lists
tcache是一个单链表
so tcache is a singly linked list
Fast Bins也是一个单链表
Fast Bins is also a singly linked list
Fast Bins的工作原理和 tcache 非常相似
so Fast Bins is going to work pretty similar to tcache when we talk about it
然而，至于 unsorted bin ，small bins 和 large bins
however for unsorted bin small bins and large bins
它们是双链表
these are doubly linked lists
前向和后向指针会参与到
and so the forward and backward pointer are going to be involved
这3种bin里随意一个bin的任意3个节点的联系
for any three chunks that are in these three bins
我们看一下双链表的样子
so let's take a look at what the doubly linked list kind of looks like
双链表意味着有一个前向指针和一个后向指针
so a doubly linked list means that we have a forward pointer and a backward pointer
现在它仍然和 tcache 相似
now it's going to still be similar to tcache
或者说与单链表机制相似
or kind of our singly linked list mechanism in the sense that
以 small bin 为例
for the small bins for example
还是会有一个头指针
there is going to be a head pointer
它是进入链表的入口点
that's the entry point into the list
头指针指向链表中的一个chunk
and that head pointer is going to point to one of the chunks
区别在于
the difference is
既能通过每个chunk的forward指针，在一个方向前进
every one of these chunks can be navigated in one direction via the forward pointer
直到它遍历回到第一 chunk
until it loops back around to chunk one
也能通过后向指针反方向后退
or they can be navigated in the reverse order by repeatedly calling the back pointer
直到它绕回来
until it loops back around
所以你可以看到这两个链表都是循环的
and so you see how both of these lists are cyclic
无论我是前进还是后退
whether I navigate the forward direction or the backwards direction
我都可以回到第一个chunk
I can come back to chunk1
所以这个头指针并没有实际方向
and so the head pointer is not really directional
它只是简单地指向一个 chunk
it simply points to a chunk
那么为什么要用双链表而不是
so why use a doubly linked list instead of a
像tcache一样，用单链表
single linked list like what we've seen with tcache
好吧
well
答案是
the answer is
双链表能更有效地删除节点
a doubly linked list allows for a lot more efficient removal of items
因为更新它不需要遍历整个链表
because we don't have to traverse the entire list to update it
至于为什么会
and the reason that we're going to be
相比tcache，要更频繁地从链表中，更新或删除节点
updating removing items from these lists more frequent basis than we do with tcache
是因为要合并
is because of something that's known as consolidation
当两个相邻的空闲 chunk
consolidation occurs when two neighboring chunks
我说的相邻 chunk 是指，在虚拟内存中紧挨着的两个 chunk
and when I say neighboring chunks I mean two chunks that are right next to each other in virtual memory
会合并，生成一个更大的 chunk
are merged to create one larger chunk
这个合并，可能会发生在free的过程中
now this consolidation step can occur when a chunk is freed
这可以理解
and that makes some sense
释放一个 chunk
I free the chunk
我们会把它传递给堆
we're passing it into the heap
相邻chunk可能也是空闲的
the neighbor may be free
所以我们把它们合并成一个
we merge them together into one
但是malloc时也会发生合并
but it can also occur when a chunk is mallocd
乍一看，这是没有道理的
and at face value it doesn't make sense
为什么调用malloc会导致合并发生
why calling malloc would cause consolidation to occur
因为当程序调用malloc时
because when a program calls malloc
它在请求一个 chunk
it's requesting a chunk
但因为 一些堆的内部机制
but based upon kind of some of the internal mechanisms of the heap
和缓存层的工作原理
and how some of these caching layers in bins work
调用malloc确实会导致堆
the active calling malloc can cause the heap
去合并它在内部跟踪的 chunk
to consolidate chunks that it is tracking internally
这种主动整合需要
and this active consolidation requires
在合并发生时，从这些bin中删除被合并的chunk的记录
the removal of chunk entries from these bin lists when that merging occurs
这在内存中是什么样子的呢
so what does this look like physically in memory
注意：不在链表中，而是在内存中
not in the lists but in memory
合并能发生在向前和向后2个方向
well consolidation can occur both in the forward and backward direction
要合并
and in order for it to occur
chunk 的P位就得是0
the P bit must be cleared for a chunk to consolidate
如果你还记得的话
if you recall
P位表示先前的 chunk 正在被使用
the P bit indicates that the prior chunk is in use
这里有在内存中挨着的chunk1和chunk2
so right here we have chunk1 and chunk2 right next to each other contiguous in memory
chunk2的P位显示chunk1在使用中
chunk2's P bit indicates that chunk1 is allocated
chunk1的P位显示它前面的chunk在使用中
chunk1's P bit indicates that the chunk before chunk1 is allocated
chunk2怎么知道chunk1在哪里
now how does chunk2 know where chunk1 is
它不是通过前向和后向指针来获知
it's not from the forward and backward pointer
这些指针是用来定位bin中chunk节点的位置的
these forward and backward pointers have to do with tracking chunks in lists or bins
如果要识别内存中相邻chunk的位置
as far as identifying chunks as far as where they are in memory contiguously
chunk2会用它的prev_size来计算
chunk2 would look at its previous size to calculate
内存中的前一个chunk 的地址
where is the prior chunk in memory
记住，合并时的前后（内存前后）
so remember there is a difference between moving through memory contiguously for merging
和更新链表指针时的前后（节点前后）是不同的
and updating the forward and backward pointers of the lists
举个例子
so let's take this as an example here
初始状态有三个 chunk
I have three chunks as an initial state
Chunk1 2和3
chunk1 2 and 3
这三个 chunk 都在使用中
all three of these chunks are allocated
chunk3 P位为1，表示chunk2在使用
now chunk 3 has its P bit set.  because chunk2 is allocated
chunk2 P位为1，表示chunk1在使用
chunk2 has its p bit set because chunk1 is allocated
chunk1 P位为1
chunk1 has its P bit set
虽然这里没展示
because I don't have it in this example
但在chunk1前，有一个在使用的chunk0
but there would be some chunk 0 behind chunk1 which is currently allocated
当free chunk1时会发生什么
what happens when we call free on chunk1
首先chunk1被释放了
well chunk1 is freed
这意味着它将被插入到某个链表或者说bin中
this means that it's going to get inserted into some list or bin
不管被插入到哪个bin
it doesn't matter what bin it is
当发生时
and when that occurs
会写入 chunk1 的 fd 和 bk 指针
the chunk1 is going to get a forward pointer written and a backward pointer written
如果插入的是large bin ，还会写入额外2个指针
it may get two additional pointers after that  if it is a large bin chunk
但我们稍后会讲到这点
but we'll cover that a little bit later
可以确定的是，会写入 fd 和 bk 指针
one thing that will occur though is the forward and backward pointer
它们会作为元数据加入，因为这是一个空闲 chunk
well it will get added as metadata because it's a free chunk
现在我们看到 chunk2 这里也有一些变化
now chunk2 we see that there were some changes there as well
尽管我们释放的是chunk1
even though what we freed was chunk1
在释放chunk1时
by freeing chunk1
会去更新chunk2 的元数据
we are updating the metadata in chunk2
chunk2现在有一个有效的 prev_size 值
chunk2 now has a previous size value
之前这里的值是无效的
where before it wasn't necessarily going to be there
能看到 chunk2 的 prev_size 被改为 0x120
we see that the previous size for chunk2  is updated to hex 120
还能看到，chunk2 size中的P位，被清掉了
we also see that the P bit is recleared from chunk2's size
原来 size 是 0x101，因为 P位是1
so it would have been hex 101 because the p bit would be set
现在清除了P位，就变成了0x100
and by clearing that, it becomes hex 100
当然 chunk2 的实际大小一直是 0x100
but the actual size of chunk2 is hex 100
最低3个有效位只是用于跟踪A M和P标志
the least significant bits there are just tracking the A M and P flags
到目前为止，还没有什么特别的事情发生
so far nothing fancy has really occurred
我们只是更新了一些元数据
we've just updated some metadata
但如果我们释放chunk2，会怎样
but what happens if we were to free the allocation that corresponds to chunk2
好吧
well
当我们释放chunk2时
when we free chunk2
先更新 chunk2 的前向和后向指针
we would need to update the metadata of chunk2 with a forward and backward pointer
然后 清除 chunk3 的P位
we would then clear the prior in use bit that is in chunk 3
我们可以在这里看到发生了
which we see occurs
然后用 chunk2的size 更新了 chunk3的 prev_size
and in the previous size for chunk3 gets updated to show the size of chunk2
但如果chunk1和chunk2发生合并，会怎样
but what happens if these two chunks chunk1 and chunk2 get consolidated
这两个chunk被合并成一个更大的chunk
well the active consolidation combines these chunks into one larger chunk
在释放chunk2时，它知道自己要被合并
now chunk2 when it's freed can know that it's a candidate for consolidation
它能知道自己要被合并
and it knows it's a candidate for consolidation
是因为 chunk2 的P位为0
because chunk2's previous in use bit is not set
通过 chunk2 的P位为0
它知道了 在内存中它前一个chunk 也是空闲的
it knows that the chunk behind it in memory is also free
所以要把他俩合并成一个更大的
so it makes sense to combine these two chunks into one larger allocation
能在这里看到它发生
and we can see that happen right here
能看到 chunk1 的大小被更新成 chunk1的大小 + chunk2的大小
we see that the size of chunk1 gets updated to be the size of chunk1+ the size of chunk2
也能看到 chunk3 的 P位 还是0
we also see that chunk3's previous in use bit still clear
因为合并后的 chunk 仍然是空闲的
because the combined chunk after consolidation is still free
但改变了chunk3 的 prev_size
but what does change is chunk 3's previous size
chunk3 的prev_size 之前是 0x100
chunk 3's previous size was hex 100
这没问题，因为之前是 chunk2的大小
and that was correct because that's the size of chunk2
但合并后
but when consolidation occurs the
chunk3 前面的是 chunk1
next immediate chunk behind chunk 3 is now chunk1
一个更大的 chunk1
and it's a larger chunk1
所以 chunk3 的 prev_size 现在是 0x220
so the previous size of chunk 3 gets updated to Hex 220
这很好
so that's great and all
这就是（虚拟）内存中发生的
and that's what occurs in physical memory
记住，这是发生在虚拟内存中
because remember this is in physical memory
是在一个连续的内存中
so we're in a contiguous memory region here
从 0xa010 到 0xa650
from Hex a010 to Hex a650 in this example
但 从这些链表中看呢
but what about these lists
还是没解释
that still doesn't explain
为什么我们需要一个双链表
why we need a doubly linked list
在我们的例子中
well in our example here
我们释放的是chunk2
what we freed was chunk2
这样一来，chunk2就消失了
and by doing that chunk2 disappeared
因为它和chunk1合并了
because it consolidated with chunk1
所以有一个列表
so if I have a list
不管是哪种bin
in any of these bins here
它记录着chunk
that is tracking chunks
chunk2曾经在这个列表中
chunk2 used to be in this list
但是当合并发生时
but when consolidation occurs
我们需要从列表中删除chunk2
we need to remove chunk2 from the list
现在我知道chunk2在哪里
now I know where chunk2 is
但我不一定知道它在哪个链表
but I don't necessarily know what list it's in
我不清楚堆的状态
because I don't know the state of the heap
所以有没有办法可以直接更新chunk2所在的列表
so is there a way that I can update the list that chunk2 is in
而不需要遍历所有的链表
without having to traverse all of these lists and try and figure out where is chunk2
答案是肯定的
the answer is yes
这就是用双链表的原因
and that's why we have this doubly linked list
不管chunk2在哪个列表中
no matter what list chunk2 is in
先取出 chunk2前面chunk的后向指针
we can take the forward backward pointer
并将其设置为chunk2的后向指针
and set it to chunk2's backward pointer
再取出chunk2后面chunk的前向指针
and we can take chunk2's backward forward pointer
并将其设置为chunk2的前向指针
and set it to chunk2's forward pointer
这将把chunk2从它所在的列表中移除，不管它在哪里
and this will remove chunk2 from whatever list it is in regardless of where it is
这就是为什么
and this is why
使用双链表可以非常快速地删除链表中chunk
having a doubly linked list allows for very rapid removal of chunks from the list
这个有点拗口
now that was a little bit of a mouthful
最终的结果就是，我们可以删掉chunk2
but the end result is we can remove chunk2
且只需要查看chunk2元数据中的指针
while only looking at the pointers that exist in the metadata of chunk2
不管这是一个large bin ，small bin 还是unsorted bin
and so it doesn't matter whether this was a large bin a small bin an unsorted bin
我们不用担心这个
we don't have to worry about that
只要我们遵循这个算法
as long as we follow the lb unlinking algorithm
就能从对应链表中删除chunk
we'll be removing the chunk from whatever list it happens to be in
这在代码中是什么样子的呢
now what does this unlinking look like in code
这是libc中unlink_chunk函数的开始
well this is the beginning of the unlink_chunk function in libc
如果你想深入了解，可以点击幻灯片上的链接
you can click the link in the slide here if you want to take a deeper look at it
现在我们看到的是，当chunk被解除链接时
now what we see here is that when a chunk is unlinked
这里在删除 chunk p
so we're trying to unlink a chunk p
先保存 p 的 fd
well we save the forward value of the chunk we're unlinking
保存 p 的 bk
we save the backward value of the chunk that we're unlinking
然后开始删除或者说解除链接
then to perform the removal or the unlinking
做法和之前的描述完全相同
we do exactly what I had just described
这里的 fd->bk
the forward backward pointer
是 p 在链表中前一个chunk 的后向指针
which is the chunk that is next in the list its previous entry
它将被改成当前在删除的 p 的 bk
is going to be whatever is previous to us to the chunk that's being unlinked
这里的 bk 的 fd，也是如此
similarly the backwards forwards pointer
p的fd
so the next entry of whatever is behind us in the list
会被设置到 bk 的 fd 中
gets set to whatever is in front of us in the list
我们不用管我们在哪个列表中
and we don't have to worry about what list we're in
这能非常快速有效地从bin中移除 chunk
and this provides very rapid and efficient removal of chunks from these bin lists
我们之后会更深入地研究一下这些检查
now we'll take a deeper look at this little bit later
但现在绝对值得一提
but it's definitely worth mentioning right now
能看到有一些检查，用于确保这些值的正确性
that we see there are checks here to make sure that these values are correct
先快速看一下这第一个检查
we take a quick look at this first check up here
这个检查确保
there is a check that ensures the chunk size
正在被删除的chunk的大小
that of the chunk that is being removed or unlinked
也就是p的大小
which is p
如果它不等于下一个chunk的prev_size
this if this does not equal the previous size of the next chunk
那就有问题了，说明 size 被破坏了
then there's a problem we've corrupted the size
这是有道理的
and that makes some sense
当前 chunk 的 size
the size of the current chunk
应该等于内存中下一个 chunk 的prev_size
should equal the previous size of the next chunk in contiguous memory
下面这里还有一个检查
now there's another check down here
是
and this check says
链表中下一个chunk的后向指针
the backward entry of the next chunk in the list
应该指向当前 chunk
should equal the current chunk
链表中上一个 chunk 的前向指针
and the forward at forward entry of the prior chunk in a list
应该指向当前 chunk
should equal the current chunk
其实就是 往前走一步，在退一步
and all this is doing is jumping forward and back
确保还在原来的位置
and making sure we end up in the same spot
回退一步，再前进一步
and then jumping backwards and forwards on these pointers
确保还在原地
and making sure we end up in the same spot
对于一个正常运行的堆
so for a correctly functioning heap
这些检查不会出问题
these are assumed correct
但在漏洞利用的情景下，这些值可能被操纵
but in an exploitation scenario where these values may be manipulated
这些检查将导致许多问题和错误消息
these checks will be the cause of a lot of problems and error messages
现在绝对值得一提
definitely worth mentioning now
因为随着模块的深入，您将看到这些错误消息
because you'll be seeing these error messages as we move forward in the module